Simon Fraser University Women's Centre fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser University Women's Centre fonds
1972 - 2000; predominant 1974-1999
F-40
Q106068500
3.13 m of textual records 89 photographs 4 slides 9 sound recordings 2 artifacts
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PARALLEL TITLES OR OTHER TITLE INFO In the first arrangement and description (in 2001), the fonds was titled "Simon Fraser Student Society Women's Centre." The Archives changed the fonds title in 2009 to reflect the name by which the Centre is commonly known. GENERAL NOTE Location of non-textual media: - Photographs are found in series F-40-5-7, Photographs. - Audio recordings are found in series F-40-6, Reference files (7 audio cassettes). - Artifacts (a button and a pin from the December 6 vigil in 1993) are found in file F-40-5-2-0-3, December 6 Vigil, 1993 (series F-40-5-2, Celebrations and special events files).
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of Canada through the National Archives of Canada and the Canadian Council of Archives' Control of Holdings Program (March 2001); the SFU Faculty of Arts (February 2000); the SFU Department of Women's Studies (February 2000); the SFU Department of History (March 2000); and the SFU Women's Centre Collective (March 2000). Funding for processing subsequent accruals was provided by the Government of Canada through the National Archival Development Program, a program delivered by the Canadian Council of Archives in partnership with Library and Archives Canada (March 2009).
Simon Fraser University Women's Centre
The SFU Women's Centre was established in 1974 and continues as of this writing (2009) as an active organization. Funded by the Simon Fraser Student Society (SFSS) as a constituency group, the Women's Centre provides programming, space and volunteer opportunities to self-identified women on campus, and resource information and peer support to women and men.
The Women's Centre began in 1974 when a group of women students revived the SFU Women's Caucus (originally established in 1968) and obtained SFSS club status. It opened the Women's Centre that year in a small room in the Rotunda. In 1980 the Centre moved to the Academic Quadrangle, then in 1996 back to the Rotunda (TC3013), doubling its physical space to approximately 1400 square feet.
The Centre's organizational structure has evolved over time. The Women's Centre Steering Committee developed out of the Women's Caucus, but by 1977 it had merged with the Women's Centre Collective. The Collective consists of women students who volunteer a set number of hours per week to staff the Centre and remains the decision-making body of the Centre. In 1979-80, the Women's Centre Board was created to formulate policy, promote the Centre, liaise with the university community, locate funding sources, and work closely with the Collective, which continued to be responsible for day-to-day operations and activities. The Board included representatives from SFSS, the Women's Centre Collective, the Women's Studies Department, the Women's Studies Student Union, and female administrative and clerical university staff. By the mid-1980s the Board was meeting irregularly; it was discontinued in 1990, its functions transferred to a newly created part-time paid position of Coordinator, funded by and reporting to the SFSS.
The Women's Centre provides a number of services, including a women-only lounge open 24 hours a day, a resource office, peer support, library, kitchen facilities, study carrels, couches and a quiet play area for children in the lounge. Men can access the Centre's library materials, peer support, and referral information.
Since its establishment, the Centre has undertaken numerous activities and projects. In cooperation with other campus groups, the Centre promoted the creation of a Women's Studies Department, the institution of a university harassment policy and office, the improvement of campus childcare facilities, and the organization of International Women's Day events, December 6 vigils, and women's self-defense classes.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the organization. Series titles were supplied by the archivist and are typically based on the contents of the series (exceptions will be noted in series descriptions). At the file and item level, titles reflect the records creator's original usage.
Fonds consists of records made or received by the Women's Centre in the course of carrying out its functions and programs. The geographical focus of the activities documented is the Lower Mainland of British Columbia and especially the Simon Fraser University campus in Burnaby. Activities documented include provision of facilities, resources and referral services; meetings of the Women's Centre Collective and the Women's Centre Board; correspondence and liaison with other individuals and groups; Centre funding, budget planning and management of its financial resources; planning and organization of projects, programs and events; and maintenance of library and reference material. Records include logbooks, correspondence, reports, account books and summaries, minutes and meeting support papers, brochures, handbooks, photographs, reference files and audio cassettes.
Records were originally used and maintained by the Women's Centre as a single unit of office files. In 2001 the Archives arranged the material into seven series (with some additional sub-series) in order to facilitate intellectual access to the documents by grouping records that were generated by similar functions and activities. During the 2009 processing of subsequent accruals, the archivist added a new series (F-40-8, Liaison and cooperation files) and re-organized what had been a single series (series 5) into several sub-series (see F-40-5, Education, advocacy and outreach files). The latter re-organization affected a number of files that had previously been assigned reference codes; see appendix D for a concordance between the former file numbers and the new ones. Researchers should be aware that overlap among groupings occurs, and the entire file list for the fonds should be reviewed to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject.
Within series, files are typically arranged chronologically; exceptions only will be noted in series descriptions. Within files, documents are generally organized chronologically, though strict chronological order was not always originally maintained within files nor has it been supplied by the archivist.
Simon Fraser Student Society; Photographic materials; Sound recordings; Textual records; Women
The Archives acquired the records directly from the Women's Centre in two accessions (1997 and 2003).
As of April 2009, all accessions have been processed. According to the Agreement to Transfer signed by the Women's Centre and the Archives in 1997, the Centre will donate its inactive records to the Archives once every five years. Further accruals are therefore expected. Series should be considered "open-ended" (i.e. further accruals expected) unless otherwise indicated in the series description.
The Archives has acquired the records of a number of other women's organizations. Consult the archivist for details.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File lists are available. Item lists of audio-cassettes in series 6 are available. Appendices to this finding aid include copies of articles dealing with the Centre's history (Appendix B), and an extended administrative history with contributions by Professor Andrea Lebowitz (SFU) and Leah Georgia, Women's Centre Coordinator (Appendix C). Appendices are available in the hard-copy and pdf versions of the finding aids.
- Correspondence files, 1974 - 1999; F-40-1; 29 cm of textual records; Note that there is a gap in the series and that correspondence for the years 1987-1991 inclusive is missing.
  published
  Series consists of correspondence conducted by the Women's Centre with campus and off-campus individuals and organizations, including university administrators, the Simon Fraser Student Society, the Women's Studies Coordinating Committee, the Vancouver Status of Women, and the Women's Building Society of Vancouver. Activities documented include requests for information; support and participation in events and projects; funding proposals; and liaison with other groups and organizations. Records consist of correspondence.
  Simon Fraser Student Society; Women's Studies Coordinating Committee; Vancouver Status of Women; Women's Building Society of Vancouver
  Records relating to Women's Centre projects and interventions on campus issues and controversies are mainly found in series F-40-5, Education, advocacy and outreach files; for other records relating to funding proposals and budget planning, see series F-40-2, Financial records.
  - Correspondence - outgoing, 1974 - 1975; F-40-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Correspondence - incoming, 1974 - 1976; F-40-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - Simon Fraser Student Society, 1975 - 1990; F-40-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - Vancouver Status of Women, 1975 - 1979; F-40-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - loose, 1975 - 1991; F-40-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - Lesbianism, [ca 1976] - [ca 1981]; F-40-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence, 1979; F-40-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence, 1979 - 1980; F-40-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - Women's Building Society of Vancouver, 1979 - 1982; F-40-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - National Union of Students, 1980 - 1981; F-40-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence, 1981 - 1982; F-40-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence - rape laws, 1981 - 1982; F-40-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence, 1981 - 1983; F-40-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 40-1)
  - Correspondence 1/2, 1982; F-40-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Correspondence 2/2, 1982; F-40-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Correspondence - Women's Studies Coordinating committee, 1982 - 1984; F-40-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Correspondence, 1984; F-40-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Correspondence 1/2, 1984 - 1986; F-40-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Correspondence 2/2, 1984 - 1986; F-40-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Correspondence, 1992; F-40-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
    Restricted in whole
  - Correspondence, 1993 - 1994; F-40-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Women's Studies Coordinating Committee -- minutes, 1975 - 1976; F-40-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Women's Studies Coordinating Committee -- minutes, 1985 - 1989; F-40-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Correspondence - outgoing, vol. 1, 1989 - 1999; F-40-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Correspondence - outgoing, vol. 2, 1989 - 1999; F-40-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Suggestion box queries and responses, 1992 - 1993; F-40-1-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Lounge 93-94 - suggestion box and comment book, 1993 - 1994; F-40-1-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
- Financial records, 1974 - 1988; F-40-2; 5 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the funding of the Women's Centre and its management of financial resources. Activities documented include funding proposals and grant applications, budget planning and approval, and review and management of accounts. Records consist of correspondence, proposals, reports, budgets, financial statements, account books and ledgers, and grant applications and supporting documentation.
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  Other records relating to funding proposals may also be included in the Centre's general correspondence; see series F-40-1, Correspondence files.
  - Accounts book, 1981 - 1986; F-40-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Budget planning, 1975 - 1988; F-40-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Expense accounts, 1974 - 1975; F-40-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Financial statements, 1975 - 1977; F-40-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - General journal - revenue and asset accounts, 1974 - 1975; F-40-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
  - Grants and applications, 1975; F-40-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 40-2)
- Logbooks, 1979 - 1999; F-40-3; 41 cm of textual records
  Series comprises records created by Women's Centre staff to document day-to-day operations, staff activities and messages, and women's use of the Centre's facilities. Records include logbooks (1979-1992) containing daily entries by staff recording work completed, messages, phone calls, proposals, comments and opinions, and occasional correspondence; daily work reports (1984-1986) tabulating the number of phone calls and drop-ins by category; mail logs (1991) registering incoming and outgoing mail; phone logs (1991); and sign-in books (1988-1992) signed by women using the Centre, recording name, date, purpose or other comments relating to the visit.
  The archivist initially arranged the files (in 2001) to group together similar types of documents; the 2009 accruals were simply added in chronological order.
  - Daily work reports, 1984 - 1986; F-40-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1979; F-40-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1980; F-40-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1981; F-40-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1983; F-40-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1984; F-40-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1985; F-40-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1986; F-40-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1987; F-40-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1988; F-40-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1989; F-40-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 40-3)
  - Logbook, 1990; F-40-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Logbook, 1991; F-40-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Logbook 1/3, 1992; F-40-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Logbook 2/3, 1992; F-40-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Logbook 3/3, 1992; F-40-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Mail log, 1991; F-40-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Phone log, 1991; F-40-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Sign-in book, 1988 - 1989; F-40-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Sign-in book, 1990; F-40-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Sign-in book, 1991 - 1992; F-40-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Confidential documents removed from files, 1985 - 1990; F-40-3-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 40-4)
  - Daily log sheets, 1994; F-40-3-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Daily log sheets, 1995; F-40-3-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Daily log sheets, 1996; F-40-3-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 40-15)
  - Daily log sheets, 1997; F-40-3-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 40-16)
  - Daily log sheets, vol. 1, 1998; F-40-3-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 40-16)
  - Daily log sheets, vol. 2, 1998; F-40-3-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 40-16)
  - Daily log sheets, vol. 1, 1999; F-40-3-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 40-16)
  - Daily log sheets, vol. 2, 1999; F-40-3-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 40-16)
  - Sign-in book, 1994 - 1996; F-40-3-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 40-16)
- Organization records, 1974 - 1998; F-40-4; 37 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the evolution of the Women's Centre as an organization. Activities documented include the development of Centre policies, procedures and organizational structure; meetings of the Women's Centre Steering Committee, the Women's Centre Collective and the Women's Centre Board; and participation of the Women's Centre Coordinator in Simon Fraser Student Society (SFSS) staff meetings. Records consist of agendas, minutes, correspondence, proposals, reports, and handbooks.
  The arrangement of the series into sub-series was provided by the archivist in order to faciliate intellectual access to the records. Separate sub-series were established for the meeting records of separate committees or bodies, while sub-series 4 ("policies and organization files") brings together records relating to the governance of the organization as a whole. Sub-series 6, 7 and 8 were added in 2009 to accommodate accruals.
  - Women's Centre Steering Committee meeting minutes, 1974 - 1976; F-40-4-1; 1 cm of textual records; Simon Fraser University Women's Centre Steering Committee
    The SFU Women's Centre Steering Committee developed out of the revived SFU Women's Caucus in 1974 with the opening of the SFU Women's Centre. By 1977 the Committee had merged into the Women's Centre Collective, the decision-making body of the Centre.
    Sub-series consists of the records of the Women's Centre Steering Committee meetings and includes agendas, minutes, proposals, reports and other meeting support papers.
    - Steering committee meeting minutes, 1974 - 1976; F-40-4-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
      Open
  - Women's Centre Collective meeting minutes, 1977 - 1997; F-40-4-2; 11 cm of textual records; Simon Fraser University Women's Centre Collective
    The Women's Centre Collective was established by 1977, having developed out of its predecessors, the Women's Caucus and the Women's Centre Steering Committee, which opened the SFU Women's Centre in 1974. The Collective has remained the core decision-making body of the organization and is responsible for the day-to-day operations and activities of the Centre. Since 1990, the Collective has been assisted by a paid part-time Coordinator, a position funded by and reporting to the Simon Fraser Student Society (SFSS). The Collective consists of women students who volunteer a set number of hours per week to staff the Centre. The Collective meets regularly, with the positions of chair and minute-recorder rotating weekly to different Collective members.
    Sub-series consists of the minutes of the Women's Centre Collective meetings and includes agendas, minutes, proposals, reports and other meeting support papers.
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1977; F-40-4-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1980; F-40-4-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1981; F-40-4-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1982; F-40-4-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - General meetings, 1982 - 1983; F-40-4-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1983; F-40-4-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1984; F-40-4-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1985; F-40-4-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1986; F-40-4-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1987; F-40-4-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1988; F-40-4-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, 1989; F-40-4-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Collective meeting minutes, vol. 1, 1994 - 1997; F-40-4-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 40-17)
    - Collective meeting minutes, vol. 2, 1994 - 1997; F-40-4-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 40-17)
  - Women's Centre Board meeting minutes, 1980 - 1990; F-40-4-3; 2 cm of textual records; Simon Fraser University Women's Centre Board
    The Women's Centre Board was established in the 1979-1980 re-organization of the SFU Women's Centre. The Board was created to formulate policy, liaise with the university community, locate funding sources, and work closely with the Women's Centre Collective which was responsible for the Centre's day-to-day operations and activities. The Board consists of representatives of the Simon Fraser Student Society (SFSS), the Women's Centre Collective, the Women's Studies Department, the Women's Studies Student Union, and female administrative and clerical university staff. By the mid-1980s, the Board was meeting irregularly. In 1990, it ceased operations and its functions were transferred to a newly created paid part-time position (Women's Centre Coordinator) funded by and reporting to the SFSS.
    Sub-series consists of the reocrds of the Women's Centre Board meetings and includes agendas, minutes, proposals, reports and other meeting support papers.
    - Minutes, 1980 - 1982; F-40-4-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Minutes, 1984 - 1990; F-40-4-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
  - Women's Centre policies and organization files, 1989 - 1996; F-40-4-4; 4 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the development of Women's Centre policies, procedures and organizational structure. Records includes the Women's Centre Handbook, procedures relating to workmen in the Women's Centre, and guidelines for managing the Centre's vertical files and newsletter lists.
    - Women's Centre handbook for Collective members, 1989; F-40-4-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-5)
    - Procedure - workmen in the Women's Centre, 1989; F-40-4-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-17)
    - Women's Centre handbook (revised), office copy, 1989 - 1993; F-40-4-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 40-17)
    - Vertical files -- guidelines for putting clippings in the vertical file, 1995; F-40-4-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 40-17)
    - Newsletters -- Direction Guide for Newsletter List, 1996; F-40-4-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 40-17)
  - Simon Fraser Student Society staff meeting minutes, 1991 - 1995; F-40-4-5; 13 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records arising from the participation of the Women's Centre Coordinator in the Simon Fraser Student Society (SFSS) montly staff meetings. The post of Women's Centre Coordinator was created and funded in 1991 as an SFSS staff position, initially reporting to the Administrative Services Committee (1991-2001), then subsequently to the SFSS Executive and SFSS Board of Directors. The Coordinator works with the Women's Centre Collective to oversee the operations, activities, services and programs of the Centre. Records consist of the Coordinator's copies of agendas, minutes, proposals, reports and other meeting support papers.
    Simon Fraser Student Society
    For the archives of the SFSS, see F-74, Simon Fraser Student Society fonds.
    - Minutes, 1991; F-40-4-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 40-6)
    - Minutes, 1992; F-40-4-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 40-6)
    - Minutes, 1993; F-40-4-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 40-6)
    - Minutes, 1993; F-40-4-5-0-4 (Archival box - standard 40-6)
    - Minutes, 1994 - 1995; F-40-4-5-0-5 (Archival box - standard 40-6)
  - Women's Centre planning files, 1991 - 1998; F-40-4-6; 5 cm of textual records